RAFAEL IRIZARRY: We are ready to learn about confidence intervals.
Confidence intervals are a very useful concept that
are widely used by data scientists.
A version of these that are very commonly seen come from the ggplot
geometry geom_smooth().
Here&#39;s an example using some weather data.
We write the code like this and we get a picture that looks like this.
We will later learn how this curve is formed, but note
the shaded area around the curve.
This shaded area is created using the concept of confidence intervals.
In our competition, we were asked to give an interval.
If the interval you submit includes the actual proportion p,
you get half the money you spent on your poll
back and pass to the next stage of the competition.
One way to pass to the second round of the competition
to report a very large interval-- for example, the interval 0 to 1.
This is guaranteed to include p.
However, with an interval this big, we have
no chance of winning the competition.
Similarly, if you are an election forecaster
and predict the spread will be between negative 100 and 100,
you&#39;ll be ridiculed for stating the obvious.
Even a smaller interval such as saying that the spread will
be between minus 10% and 10% will not be considered serious.
On the other hand, the smaller the interval
we report, the smaller our chance of passing to the second round.
Similarly, a bold pollster that reports very small intervals
and misses the mark most of the time will not be considered a good pollster.
We want to be somewhere in between.
Confidence intervals will help us get there.
We can use the statistical theory we have learned to compute,
for any given interval, the probability that it includes p.
Similarly if we are asked to create an interval with, say,
a 95% chance of including p, we can do that as well.
These are called 95% confidence intervals.
Note that when pollsters report an estimate and a margin of error,
they are, in a way, reporting a 95% confidence interval.
Let&#39;s show how this works mathematically.
We want to know the probability that the interval X-bar minus 2 times
the estimated standard error to X-bar plus 2 times
its estimated standard error contains the actual proportion p.
First, note that the start and end of this interval are random variables.
Every time that we take a sample, they change.
To illustrate this, we&#39;re going to run a Monte Carlo simulation.
We&#39;re going to do it just twice first.
So we&#39;re going to use these parameters.
We&#39;re going to make p 0.45 and N 1,000.
Note that the interval we get when we write this code
is different from what we get if we run that same code again.
If we keep sampling and creating intervals,
we will see that this is due to random variation.
To determine the probability that the interval includes p,
we need to compute this probability.
By subtracting and dividing the same quantities
in all parts of the equation, we get that the equation
is equivalent to this.
The term in the middle is an approximately normal random variable
with expected value 0 and standard error 1, which
we have been denoting with capital Z.
So what we have is, what is the probability
of a standard normal variable being between minus 2 and 2?
And this is, we know, about 95%.
So we have a 95% confidence interval.
Note that if we want to have a larger probability, say 99%,
a 99% confidence interval, we need to multiply by whatever
z satisfies the following equation.
Note that by using the quantity that we get by typing this code,
which is about 2.576, will do it, because by definition the pnorm of what
we get when we type qnorm(0.995) is by definition 0.995.
And by symmetry, pnorm of 1 minus qnorm(0.995) is 1 minus 0.995.
So now we compute pnorm minus pnorm minus z, we get 99%.
This is what we wanted.
We can use this approach for any percentile q.
We use 1 minus (1 minus q) divided by 2.
Why this number-- because of what we just saw, 1 minus (1 minus q)
divided by 2 plus (1 minus q) divided by 2 equals q.
And we get what we want.
Also note that to get exactly 0.95, we actually
use a slightly smaller number than 2.
How do we know?
We type qnorm of 0.975 and we see that the value
that we should be using to get exactly a 95% confidence interval is 1.96.