RAFAEL IRIZARRY: What does it mean when an election forecaster tells us
that a given candidate has a 90% chance of winning?
In the context of the urn model this would
be equivalent to stating that the probability that the proportion p
of people voting for this candidate being bigger than 0.5, than 50%,
is 90%.
But as we discussed, in the urn model, p is a fixed parameter,
and it does not make sense to talk about the probability of p
being this or that.
With Bayesian statistics, we assume it is in fact random.
And then it makes sense to talk about probability.
Forecasters also use models to describe variability at different levels.
For example: sampling variability, pollster to pollster variability,
day to day variability, and election to election variability.
One of the most successful approaches used
to describe these different levels of variability
are called hierarchical models.
And hierarchical models are best explained
in the context of Bayesian statistics.
Bayesian statistics is the topic of the following videos.