RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In the 2012 presidential election,
Barack Obama won the electoral college and he won the popular vote
by a margin of 3.9%.
Let&#39;s go back to the week before the election before we knew this outcome.
Nate Silver was giving Obama a 90% chance of winning.
Yet, none of the individual polls were nearly that sure.
In fact, political commentator Joe Scarborough said during his show,
&quot;Anybody that thinks that this race is anything but a tossup right now
is such an ideologue-- they&#39;re jokes.&quot;
To which Nate Silver responded, &quot;If you think it&#39;s a tossup, let&#39;s bet.
If Obama wins, you donate $1,000 to the American Red Cross.
If Romney wins, I do.
Deal?&quot;
How is Mr. Silver so confident?
We&#39;ll illustrate what Nate Silver saw that Joe Scarborough and other pundits
did not.
We&#39;re going to use a Monte Carlo simulation.
We&#39;re going to generate results for 12 polls taken
the week before the election.
We&#39;re going to mimic the sample sizes from actual polls.
We&#39;re going to construct and report 95% confidence
intervals for each of these 12 polls.
Here&#39;s the code we&#39;re going to use.
We&#39;re going to generate the data using the actual outcome, 3.9%.
So d, the difference, the spread, is 0.039.
The sample sizes were selected to mimic regular polls.
So we see that the first one is 1,298, the second one is 533, et cetera.
We&#39;re also going to define p, the proportion of Democrats--
or actually, the proportion of people voting for Obama,
as the spread plus 1 divided by 2.
That&#39;s the formula we&#39;ve seen before.
Then we&#39;re going to use the sapply function
to construct the confidence intervals.
For each sample size for each poll, we&#39;re going to generate a sample.
We&#39;re going to take a sample of size N. Then we&#39;re going to compute
the proportion of people voting for Obama in that sample-- that&#39;s X_hat--
construct a standard error, and then return the estimate X_hat as well as
the beginning and end of the confidence interval.
We&#39;re going to do this and then we&#39;re going
to generate a data frame that has all the results.
Here are the results of the 12 polls that we generated with the Monte Carlo
simulation.
Here&#39;s a visualization of what the intervals of these pollsters
would have reported for the difference between Obama and Romney.
Not surprisingly, all 12 polls report confidence intervals
that include the election night result, which is shown with the dashed line.
This is the case because these are 95% confidence intervals.
However, all 12 poll intervals include 0,
which is shown with a solid black line.
Therefore, individually if we asked for a prediction from the pollsters,
from each individual pollster, they would have to agree with Scarborough.
It&#39;s a tossup.
Now we&#39;re going to describe how pundits are missing a key insight.
Poll aggregators, such as Nate Silver, realize
that by combining the results of different polls,
you could greatly improve precision.
By doing this, effectively we&#39;re conducting a poll
with a huge sample size.
As a result, we can report a smaller 95% confidence interval,
and therefore a more precise prediction.
Although as aggregators we do not have access to the raw poll data,
we can use mathematics to reconstruct what
we would have obtained had we made one large poll with, in this case,
11,269 people, participants.
Basically we construct an estimate of the spread-- let&#39;s call it d--
with a weighted average in the following way.
We basically multiply each individual spread by the sample size.
That&#39;s going to give us a total spread.
And then we&#39;re going to divide by the total number
of participants in our aggregated poll.
This gives us d_hat, which is an estimate of d.
Once we have an estimate of d, we can construct
an estimate for the proportion voting for Obama, which we can then
use to estimate the standard error.
Once we do this, we see that our margin of error of the aggregated poll
is 0.018.
Thus, using the weighted average, we can predict
that the spread will be 3.1% plus or minus 1.8%,
which not only includes the actual result
but is quite far from including 0.
Once we combine the 12 polls, we become quite certain that Obama
will win the popular vote.
In this figure, you can see, in red, the interval that
was created using the combined polls.
Nate Silver and other aggregators use the same approach
to predict the electoral college.
And they did very well in 2008 and 2012.
However, note that this was just a simulation to illustrate the idea.
The actual data science exercise of forecasting elections
is much more complicated and it involves statistical modeling.