RAFAEL IRIZARRY: p-values are very common in,
for example, the scientific literature.
They are related to confidence intervals,
so we introduce the concept here.
Let&#39;s consider the blue and red bead example again.
Suppose that rather than wanting to estimate
the spread or the proportion of blue, I&#39;m interested only in the question,
are there more blue beads than red beads?
Another way to ask that is, is 2p minus 1 bigger than 0?
Is the spread bigger than 0?
So suppose we take a random sample of, say, 100 beads,
and we observe 52 blue beads.
This gives us a spread of 4%.
This seems to be pointing to there being more blue beads than red beads,
because 4% is larger than 0.
52% is larger than 48%.
However, as data scientists, we need to be skeptical.
We know there is chance involved in this process,
and we can get a 52 even when the actual spread is 0.
The null hypothesis is the skeptic&#39;s hypothesis.
In this case, it would be the spread is 0.
We have observed a random variable 2 times X-bar minus 1, which in this case
is 4%, and the p-value is the answer to the question, how
likely is it to see a value this large when the null hypothesis is true?
So we write, what&#39;s the probability of X-bar minus 0.5 being bigger than 2%?
That&#39;s the same as asking, what&#39;s the chance that the spread is 4 or more?
The null hypothesis is that the spread is 0 or that p is a half.
Under the null hypothesis, we know that this quantity here, the square root
of n times X-bar minus 0.5 divided by the square root of 0.5 times 1
minus 0.5, is a standard normal.
We&#39;ve taken a random variable and divided it by its standard error
after subtracting its expected value.
So we can compute the probability, which is a p-value,
using this equation, which reduces to this equation, where
z is a standard normal.
And now we can use code to compute this.
We compute the probability, which is equal to 69% in this case.
This is the p-value.
In this case, there&#39;s actually a large chance of seeing 52 blue beads or more
under the null hypothesis that there is the same amount
of blue beads as red beads.
So the 52 blue beads are not very strong evidence,
are not very convincing, if we want to make the case that there&#39;s
more blue beads than red beads.
Note that there&#39;s a close connection between p-values and confidence
intervals.
If a 95% confidence interval of the spread does not include 0,
we can do a little bit of math to see that this implies that the p-value must
be smaller than 1 minus 95%, or 0.05.
To learn more about p-values, you can consult any statistics textbook.
However, in general, we prefer reporting confidence intervals
over p-values, since it gives us an idea of the size of the estimate.
The p-value simply reports a probability and says nothing
about the significance of the finding in the context of the problem.