RAFAEL IRIZARRY: To demonstrate the usefulness
of hierarchical models, Bayesian models, in practice,
we&#39;re going to show you a baseball example.
In sports, we use Bayesian thinking all the time, even if we don&#39;t realize it.
Let&#39;s go to the example.
Jose Iglesias is a professional baseball player.
In April 2013, when he was starting his career, he was performing rather well.
He had been to bat 20 times and he had nine hits,
which is an average of 0.450.
This average of 0.450 means Jose had been successful 45% of the times he had
batted, which is rather high historically speaking.
Note, for example, that no one has finished a season with an average
of 0.400 or more since Ted Williams did it in 1941.
To illustrate the way hierarchical models are powerful,
we will try to predict Jose&#39;s batting average at the end of the season.
In a typical season, players have about 500 or bats.
With the techniques we have learned up to now,
referred to as frequentist statistics, the best we can do
is provide a confidence interval.
We can think of outcomes for hitting as a binomial with a success rate of p.
So if the success rate is indeed 0.450, the standard error of just 20 at bats
can be computed like this.
And it&#39;s 0.111.
We can use this to construct a 95% confidence interval, which
will be from 0.228 to 0.672.
This prediction has two problems.
First, it&#39;s very large, so it&#39;s not very useful.
Second, it&#39;s centered at 0.450, which implies that our best guess is that
this relatively unknown player will break Ted Williams&#39; longstanding
record.
If you follow baseball, this last statement will seem wrong.
And this is because you&#39;re implicitly using
the hierarchical model that factors in information
from years of following baseball.
Here we show how we can quantify this intuition.
First, let&#39;s explore the distribution of batting averages
for all players with more than 500 at bats
during the seasons 2010, 2011, and 2012.
Here are the histograms.
We note that the average player had an average of 0.275.
And the standard deviation of the population of all these players
was 0.027.
So we can see already that 0.450 would be quite an anomaly,
since it is over six standard deviations away from the average.
So is Jose lucky or the best batter seen in the last 50 years?
Perhaps it&#39;s a combination of both.
But how do we decide how much of this is luck and how much of this is talent?
If we become convinced that this is just luck,
we should trade him to a team that trusts the 0.450 observation and is
maybe overestimating his potential.