RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In this video we use public polling data
organized by FiveThirtyEight for the 2016 presidential election.
The data is included as part of the dslabs package.
You can get the data by typing this code.
Here, we show you the column names of the table.
The table includes results for national polls,
as well as state polls, taken in the year before the election.
For this first illustrative example, we will
filter the data to include national polls that happened during the week
before the election.
We also remove polls that FiveThirtyEight
has determined not to be reliable, and they have graded them with a B or less.
Some polls have not been graded.
And we&#39;re going to leave these in.
Here&#39;s the code we used to filter as we just described.
We also add a spread estimate.
Remember, the spread is what we&#39;re really interested in estimating.
So, we type this code to get the spread in proportions.
For illustrative purpose, we will assume that there are only two parties,
and call p the proportion voting for Clinton,
and 1 minus p the proportion voting for Trump.
We&#39;re interested in the spread, which we&#39;ve shown is 2p minus 1.
Let&#39;s call this spread d. d is for difference.
Note that we have several estimates of this spread coming
from the different polls.
The theory we learned tells us that these estimates
are a random variable with probability distribution
that is approximately normal.
The expected value is the election night spread, d.
And the standard error is 2 times the square root of p times
1 minus p divided by the sample size N. Assuming the urn model we described
earlier are useful models, we can use this information
to construct a confidence interval based on the aggregated data.
The estimated spread is now computed like this because now the sample size
is the sum of all the sample sizes.
And if we use this, we get a standard error,
typing this code, that then leads us to a margin of error of .0066,
a very small margin of error.
So, if we were going to use this data, we would report a spread of 1.43%
with a margin of error of 0.66%.
On election night, we find out that the actual percentage
is 2.1%, which is outside of the 95% confidence interval.
So, what happened?
Was this just bad luck?
A histogram of the reported spreads shows another problem.
With this code, we can quickly make a histogram of the spreads
that we&#39;re looking at.
The data does not appear to be normally distributed,
and the standard error appears to be larger than 0.0066.
The theory is not quite working here.
To see why, notice that various pollsters are involved
and some are taking several polls a week.
Here&#39;s a table showing you how many polls each pollster
took that last week.
Let&#39;s visualize the data for the pollsters that are regularly polling.
We write this piece of code that first filters for only pollsters that
polled more than 6 times.
And then we simply plot the spreads estimated by each pollster.
Each one has between five and six.
This plot reveals an unexpected result. First
note that the standard error, predicted by theory for each poll--
now, we&#39;re going to do this poll by poll--
gives us values between 0.018 and 0.033.
This appears to be right.
This appears to be consistent with what we see in the plot.
However, there appears to be differences across the polls.
This is not explained by the theory.
Note for example, how the USC Dornsife/LA Times
pollster is predicting a 4% win for Trump
while Ipsos is predicting a win larger than 5% for Clinton.
The theory of learned says nothing about different pollsters producing polls
with different expected values.
All the polls should have the same expected value,
the actual spread, the spread we will see on election night.
FiveThirtyEight refers to these differences as &quot;house effects.&quot;
We can also call them pollster bias.
Rather than use urn model theory, we&#39;re instead
going to develop a data-driven model to produce a better estimate and a better
confidence interval.