RAFAEL IRIZARRY: We can run a Monte Carlo
simulation to confirm that, in fact, a 95% confidence interval includes p 95%
of the time.
We write the simulation like this.
We&#39;re going to write the simulation we&#39;ve been writing.
But now, we&#39;re going to actually construct the confidence
interval inside the call to replicate.
And in the very final line, we&#39;re going to ask, is p included in the interval.
We&#39;re going to return either true or false.
To compute how often it happened, we compute the mean
of that vector of true and false.
We run a simulation and we get 0.9522.
This plot shows you the first few confidence
intervals that were generated in our Monte Carlo simulation.
In this case, we created simulations so we know what p is.
In the plot, it&#39;s represented with a vertical black line.
Notice that you can see the confidence intervals varying.
Each time, they fall in slightly different places.
This is because they&#39;re random variables.
We also know that most of the times, p is
included inside the confidence interval. p is not moving, of course, because p
is not a random variable.
We also see that, every once in a while, we actually miss p.
These confidence intervals are shown in red.
We should only see about 5% of the intervals
in red because they&#39;re 95% confidence intervals.
This plot should help you understand what confidence intervals are
and what they mean.