RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Now we&#39;re going to get ready to explain how pollsters
fit multilevel models to public poll data
and use this to forecast election results.
In the 2008 and 2012 US presidential elections,
Nate Silver used this approach to make an almost perfect prediction
and silenced the pundits.
Since the 2008 election, other organizations
have started their own election forecasting
groups that, like Nate Silver, aggregate polling data
and use statistical models to make predictions.
In 2016, forecasters greatly underestimated Trump&#39;s chances
of winning the election.
For example, the Princeton Election Consortium gave Trump less than 1%
chance of winning the election, while the Huffington Post gave him
a 2% chance.
In contrast, FiveThirtyEight had Trump&#39;s chances of winning at 29%.
Although they didn&#39;t correctly predict him to have a higher probability,
note that 29% is a higher probability than the probability of tossing
two coins and getting two heads.
It&#39;s also much, much bigger than what the other pollsters had predicted.
By understanding statistical models and how these forecasters use them,
we will start to understand how this happened.
Although not nearly as interesting as predicting the electoral college,
the actual outcome of the election, for illustrative purposes
we will start by looking at the predictions for the popular vote.
FiveThirtyEight predicted a 3.6% advantage for Clinton.
Their interval, their prediction interval,
included the actual result of 2.1%, 48.2% for Clinton
compared to 46.1% for Trump.
They were much more confident about Clinton winning this, the popular vote,
giving her a 81.4% chance of winning.
Next, we&#39;re going to look at actual public polling data from the 2016 US
presidential election to show how models are motivated and built
to produce these predictions.