RAFAEL IRIZARRY: For each pollster, let&#39;s collect
their last-reported result before the election
using this simple piece of code.
Here&#39;s a histogram of the data for these 15 pollsters.
In the previous video, we saw that using the urn model
theory to combine these results might not be
appropriate due to the pollster effect.
Instead, we will model this spread data directly.
The new model can also be thought of as an urn
model, although the connection to the urn idea is not as direct.
Rather than having beads with zeros and ones inside the urn,
now the urn contains poll results from all possible pollsters.
We assume that the expected value of our urn
is the actual spread, which we have been calling
d, which is equal to 2p minus 1.
Now, because rather than zeros and ones our urn
contains continuous numbers between minus 1 and 1,
the standard deviation of the urn is no longer
the square root of p times 1 minus p.
Rather than just the sampling variability
we get from taking different samples of zeros and ones,
the standard error for our average now includes
the pollster-to-pollster variability.
Our new urn also includes the sample variability from the polling.
Regardless, this standard deviation is now an unknown parameter.
In statistics textbooks, the Greek symbol sigma
is used to represent this parameter.
Now in summary, we have two unknown parameters now,
the expected value d, what we want to estimate,
and the standard deviation, sigma.
Our task is to estimate d and provide inference for it.
Because we model the observed values, let&#39;s call them X1 through XN,
as a random sample from the urn, the central limit theorem
still works for the average of these values
because it&#39;s an average of independent random variables.
For a large enough sample size N, the probability distribution
of the sample average, which we&#39;ll call X-bar,
is approximately normal with expected value d and standard deviation
sigma divided by the square root of N. If we are willing to consider
N equals to 15 large enough, we can use this to construct a confidence
interval.
A problem, though, is that we don&#39;t know sigma.
But the theory tells us that we can estimate the urn model
sigma, the unobserved sigma, with the sample standard
deviation, which is defined like this with this mathematical formula.
Now note in the mathematical formula that unlike the population standard
deviation, we now divide by N minus 1.
This makes s a better estimate of sigma than if we just divided by N.
And there&#39;s a mathematical explanation for this,
which is explained in most statistics textbooks, but we don&#39;t cover it here.
Now the sd function in R computes the sample standard deviation.
So we can compute it for our data here with this simple line.
And we get that it&#39;s 0.024.
We are now ready to form a confidence interval
based on our new data-driven model.
We simply use the central limit theorem and create a confidence interval
using this simple code.
We get an average, a standard error, and then a start of 1.7%
and an end of 4.1%.
That&#39;s our 95% confidence interval using now our data-driven model.
Note that our new confidence interval is wider,
and it now incorporates the pollster variability.
It does include the election-night result of 2.1%,
and also it&#39;s small enough not to include 0.
Which means that in this particular case,
we would have been quite confident that Clinton would win the popular vote.
Now, are we now ready to declare a probability of Clinton
winning as the pollsters do?
Not yet.
In our model, d is a fixed parameter, so we can&#39;t talk about probabilities.
To provide probabilities, we&#39;ll need to learn something new.
We&#39;re going to have to learn about Bayesian statistics.
And we do that next.